<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
    <!-- try to enforce the ID-nits conventions and DTD validity -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>    <!-- items used when reviewing the document -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>  <!-- controls display of <cref> elements -->
<?rfc inline="no" ?>    <!-- when no, put comments at end in comments section,
                                otherwise, put inline -->
<?rfc editing="no" ?>   <!-- when yes, insert editing marks -->

    <!-- create table of contents (set it options).
           Note the table of contents may be omitted
         for very short documents -->

<?rfc toc="yes"?><?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>

    <!-- choose the options for the references. Some like
         symbolic tags in the references (and citations)
         and others prefer numbers. --> 
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?><?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
    <!-- these two save paper: start new paragraphs from the same page etc. -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- end of list of processing instructions -->
    <!-- Information about the document.
         categories values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
         For Internet-Drafts, specify attribute "ipr".
         (ipr values are: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667),
         Also for Internet-Drafts, can specify values for
         attributes "iprExtract", and "docName".  Note
         that the value for iprExtract is the anchor attribute
         value of a section that can be extracted, and is only
         useful when the value of "ipr" is not "full3667". -->
    <!-- TODO: verify which attributes are specified only
            by the RFC editor.  It appears that attributes
            "number", "obsoletes", "updates", and "seriesNo"
            are specified by the RFC editor (and not by
            the document author). -->

<rfc	category="std"
	ipr="trust200902"
	docName="draft-johansson-sip-tls-overview-00"
>
<front>
    <title abbrev="Overview of SIP and TLS in published IETF RFCs">
	SIP and TLS in published RFCs: Overview from an implementors point of view</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->    

    <author fullname="Olle E. Johansson" initials="O.E." surname="Johansson">
      <organization>Edvina AB</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Runbovägen 10</street>
          <city>Sollentuna</city>
          <code>SE-192 48</code>
          <country>SE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>oej@edvina.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2014" />
<!-- month="May" is no longer necessary note also, day="30" is optional -->
    
    <area>Applications area (APPS)</area>    
    
    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc, IETF fine for individual submissions -->
    
    <workgroup>UTA</workgroup>
    
    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
	
    <abstract>
	<t>
	Use of TLS in the SIP protocol is defined in multiple documents, starting with RFC 3261.
	As an implementor, the descriptions on how to use TLS in these RFCs is often incomplete and in some cases confusing. 
	</t>
	<t>
	The idea with this overview is to show how different various RFCs 
	describe use of TLS. In order to avoid this, guidelines for authors
	of IETF documents involving TLS are needed.
	</t>
	<t>
	This document is not a complete overview and is not meant to be a standards track document. It's meant to be input to the UTA working group f
	</t>
    </abstract>

</front>

<middle>

    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
	<t>
	RFC 3261 <xref target="RFC3261"/> defines how to use TLS in the SIP protocol, but
	doesn't describe the actual verification between a SIP request and a TLS server
	certificate in detail.
	RFC 5922 <xref target="RFC5922"/> updates RFC 3261 with a definition of how a SIP 
	client matches a PKIX X.509 <xref target="RFC5280"/> certificate provided by a
	TLS-enabled SIP server with the domain of a SIP request that caused the connection
	to be set up. Verification is done using the domain part of the SIP URI and the
	X.509 SubjectAltName extension of type dNSName or uniformResourceIdentifier.
	This is called "domain verification" as opposed to "host verification" in RFC 5922.
	</t>
	<t>
	Including all domains hosted by a server in a server's certificate doesn't provide for a 
	scalable and easy-managed solution. Every time a service adds a domain, a new certificate
	will need to be provided, unless TLS Server Name Identification (SNI) is used,
	where each domain can have it's own certificate. Having one certificate per domain
	and subdomain adds to the administration of a service. In addition, no known 
	commercial CA offers certificate services with SIP URI's in the certificates.
	</t>
	<t>
	Using DNSsec and DNS-based Authentication of Named Entities (DANE)<xref target="RFC6698"/>
	the chain from a SIP uri to a TLS certificate changes, as outlined in this document.
	With DNSsec, the DNS lookups are authenticated and can be verified and trusted.
	<xref target="I-D.ietf-dane-srv"/> describes a DANE-based chain of trust, matching
	the SRV host name with the contents of the certificate.
	</t>
    </section>
	<section anchor="divide" title="The big divide - provider provided security or user-controlled security?">
	<t>
	SIP has footholds in two very different worlds. It’s the old bellhead vs nethead
	discussion all over again, something that shows when looking at security solutions for SIP. 
	Some of them are traditionally Telco-focused, where the service provider provides security for the 
	users, asking the users to trust the service to handle keys, certificates and process signaling and
	media unencrypted. The traditional datacom side, to take it to the extreme, is that only end users
	can manage their own security. Security needs to be end to end in this world. These trust or ”no-trust”
	perspectives affects the proposals and makes it hard to get an overview of a single ”SIP Security Architecture” 
	- because it doesn’t exist. In true IETF spirit, there are many and in some cases incompatible, proposals.
	</t>
	<t>The SIP architecture has been developed during more than 10 years and the SIP security framework has been 
	added to in a large amount of RFCs, that doesn’t always match when combined into one solution. The addition
	of SIP outbound, Gruus, SIP connection reuse and the clarification of the SIPS uri has been huge steps forward
	in providing a solution where TLS can be used in production, compared with the initial specification in RFC 3261.
	</t>
	<t>
	There are RFCs that indicates a need for security but doesn’t provide the developer with any clear directives.
	This document tries to build a combined picture of the current state of SIP security to provide a basis for
	further work in order to both build a more clear framework that can be used to provide running code, and to
	find issues that still needs solutions.
	</t>
	<t>The document doesn’t focus on attack scenarios, media security or issues with encryption algorithms or protocols.</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations"> 
		<t>
		...
		</t>
	</section>
	
	<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations"> 
  		<t>This document does not require actions by IANA.</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    	<t>
	...
	</t>
	</section>
    
</middle>

<back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3263" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4033" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4346" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5280" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5922" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6698" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6066" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dane-srv" ?>
	 	 
    </references>
    
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5589" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ogud-dane-vocabulary" ?>
   </references>
	<section anchor="appendixa" title="Appendix A. Implementation notes">
	<t>
	Developers of SIP implementations are strongly encouraged to implement
	RFC 5922 and this document for secure verification of a SIP domain
	with a TLS server. This document also encourages implementation of TLS SNI
	both in client and server implementations. In order to get support of
	this function, update to new versions of the TLS libraries and make sure that
	the implementation supports new versions of TLS - 
	TLS 1.1 <xref target="RFC4346"/> and TLS 1.2 <xref target="RFC5246"/>.
	</t>

	</section>
  </back>
</rfc>
